During an emergency, it is normal to experience a rush of adrenaline which can narrow your focus onto a specific task and limit your ability to process surroundings.
Remember, slow is smooth and smooth is fast. We want controlled action, not panic.
Look at this picture on the screen. This is a potential emergency. What do you see? What would you do first? Should you move them?
In a situation like this, scene safety is your absolute priority. Take a moment to pause and look around.
You need to check for hazards like traffic, fire, electricity, or even aggressive animals.
If the scene is unsafe, stay back and wait for professionals like firefighters or police to secure the area.
You can't help if you're hurt.
A question that often comes up is, should I move them? The answer is only if the scene is unsafe or if you must move them to perform life-saving care.
For example, it is always okay to move someone to perform CPR.
While we want to minimize movement for things like suspected spine injuries, if there is an immediate danger like fire or oncoming traffic, it is best to move them to safety.